Now, there's a convention in situation calculus that predicates like 'at',
在情景演算中对于At 等谓词有个约定
we said plane 'p' was at airport 'x' in situation 's'.
我们说 At (p, x, s)
These types of predicates that can vary from one situation to
这些谓词的类型在不同情景中也各不相同
another are called fluents from the word fluent,
称为流 (fluents) 来自于单词流畅 (fluent)
having to do with fluidity or change over time.
与流畅度有关 或随着时间变化
And the convention is that they refer to a specific situation and we
通常它们表示特定情景
always put that situation argument as the last in the predicate.
我们总是把情景参数值放在谓词的最后
Now, the trickiest part about situation calculus is
情景演算最棘手的地方在于
describing what changes and what doesn't change as a result of an action.
描述一个动作引起了哪些变化 没有引起哪些变化
I remember in classical planning we had
我记得在经典规划中 我们曾有
action schemas where we describe one action at a time and said what changed.
动作模式 用于描述某次的一个动作 并说明变化内容
For situation calculus, it turns out to be easier to do it the other way around.
在情景演算中 通过其他方式更容易地做到这一点
Instead of writing one action,
我们不是写下一个动作
or one schema, or one axiom,
一个模式或一个公理
for each action we do one for each fluent for each predicate that can change.
对每个动作 我们为发生变化的每个谓词的流做这一点
And we use a convention called Successor-state axioms and these are
我们使用一种约定 称为后继状态公理
used to describe what happens in the state that's the successor of executing an action.
用来描述执行一个动作后 状态发生了什么
And in general, a Successor-state axiom will have the form of saying for
一般说来 后继状态公理具有表示
all actions and states if it's possible to execute action 'a' in state 's'.
所有动作和状态的形式 对于所有 a,s Poss (a, s)
Then, it will show in general what they look like here,
那么一般会展现他们的样子
then the fluent is true,
即 (fluent true
if and only if action 'a' made it true or action 'a' didn't undo it.
&lt;=&gt; a made it true ∨ a didn’t undo)
So that is either it wasn't true before and 'a' made it be
所以要么之前为假 然后把 a 变为真
true or it was true before and 'a' didn't do something to stop it being true.
或者之前为真 a 没能成为真
For example, I show you that Successor-state axiom for the 'In' predicate.
例如我在谓词 In 中向你展现后继状态公理
And just to make it a little bit simpler I'll leave out all that for all quantifiers.
为了使它更简单点 我删除了所有全称量词
So wherever you see a variable without a quantifier.
所以你见到不包含量词的变量
Assume that there is 'a' for all.
假设 对于所有 a
And what we'll say is it's possible to execute 'a' in situation 's' if that's true, then,
即 Poss (a,s) =&gt;
the 'In' predicate holds between some cargo 'c' and some plane in the state which
In (c,p,
is the result of executing action 'a' in state 's' so that 'In' predicate will hold,
result (s,a))
if and only if,
&lt;=&gt;
either 'a' was a load in action.
(a=Load(c,p,x)
So, if we load the cargo into the plane, then that results,
如果我们向飞机上装载货物
the result of executing that action 'a' is that the cargo is in the plane or
执行动作 a 的结果是货物在飞机上
it might be that it was already true that the cargo was in the plane in situation 's'.
或者已为真 即 In (c,p,s)
And 'a' is not equal to an unload action.
∧ a ≠ Unload (c,p,x))
So, for all a, and,
所以对于所有 a, s
s for which it's possible to execute 'a' in situation 's',
都可能在情景 s 中执行 a
the 'In' predicate holds if and only if,
谓词 In 成立 当且仅当
the action was a load or the 'In' predicate used
动作为加载 (load) 或谓词 In
to hold in the previous state then the action is not an unload.
已经在之前的状态中成立 并且动作不能为卸载 (unload)